Next is experiments and why you should
do them.
Uh experiments is a concept that exists
in all sorts of
of products. It involves testing
different ideas and approaches
to actually identify what's best.
Um and as benefits
it's the same benefit. It's like this is
a method uh from customer discovery. You
have the reduced risk of implementing
the wrong thing. Uh you validate
assumptions, so it's a method before
actually doing of having investment into
that specific feature.
Uh you have data-driven insights. That's
very very good. And usually you enhance
the user experience because this is what
we're talking about. Experiments can
also be like sort of AB testing, let's
say. And it prevents this solution-first
thinking. So, it encourages problem
validation rather than moving into to
solutions. You usually define an
objective and the hypothesis that you
are trying to test. Maybe you I mean you
looked into it in the hackathon as well.
But you design the experiment.
The experiment can be something super
easy uh or it can be something more
complex, more thought through. It
depends. And you of course you collect
and analyze the data and you iterate and
learn. So, here on the left-hand side
you see a small example of
um a hypothesis
that also includes the experiment that
you are trying to to do. So, if we
actually reduce the number of buttons,
which is a variable, we
make only one button rather than two or
whatever,
then we'll get more registrations. So,
we are aiming to get more registration,
which is the variable two, by reducing
the number of buttons. And we make an
experiment. We reduce the number of
buttons and see if the registrations
number
goes up. That's the same as if we make
the button red or green and see uh if we
have more clicks on it. So, this is a
small experiment. What other concepts
and types we have in experiments? We
have this hypothesis-driven
approach. So, every experiment starts
with testable hypothesis, as we said
before.
We have the independent and dependable
dependent variables,
which are what you change versus what
you measure. So, the registration versus
the number of buttons.
Uh the minimum viable experiment.
Um we talk a lot about minimum viable
product, but the minimum viable
experiment is the smallest text test
that you can do in order to get
actionable data. And you need to aim for
that because you don't have so much
money as to invest in a big experiment
that will validate all of the data.
And you should avoid bias.
Bias uh can get involved also in the
interviews that you do because also
interviews are sort of experiments.
Um
you should be very aware of that because
bias can get
um
very tricky. We have customer discovery
interviews, where you validate the
problem solution fit for different
things.
We have landing page tests, for example.
You put uh a button, register here,
we'll notice you when we are up. You
check demand.
You have this Wizard of Oz or concierge
MVPs.
Um
What these mean, and these can be used a
lot uh in terms of uh what we have now
with
AI.
This Wizard of Oz or concierge MVPs
are
clickable prototypes or not so
clickable, so staged prototypes.
When
you as the person doing the interview,
the testing,
the user says, I would go that way or I
will use this prompt or I will do that
and you tell them what happens next.
And usually you do this scenarios
yeah, by guiding the user rather than
he or she actually testing a solution.
This is also
this is useful when you test
what they expect to get as a result in
terms of
when you're building something from an
AI.
You do AB testings, that's also an
experiment where you have multiple
versions, not just AB but CD EF.
And you compare versions for conversion
impact.
You can have fake door tests. So, you
can have buttons throughout your app
that go to a different different places
that don't exist. So, you have a feature
that added something and
yeah,
it doesn't work but you count it in in
an analytics tool and you say, okay, 100
people actually clicked on it.
So, I might as well implement it.
And smoke tests. Smoke tests are usually
ads that go to a sign up page. These are
quite
used so that you see that the demand
exists.
These are some experiment cards.
I truly advise you to always document
your work. If you do it and don't
document it, it's not as valuable
because you won't be able to go back to
it and show it to other people and and
so on. So, even though it's all in your
head,
it's not. So, uh you need this
documentation that can be now filled
much easier and and so on. So, please uh
document what you are doing.